<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The heads of the great charge, presented to the Honourable House of Commons, against the eleven impeached members, by Colonel Scroope. Colonel Okey. Colonel Hewson. Colonel Pride. Lievt. Col. Bowen. Lievt. Col. Goffe Major Raynbow. Capt. Berry. Capt. Clarke. Capt. Carter. Capt Roase. Master Sexby Master Gettings. As also, certain papers from the army, setting forth the gallant proceedings of the commissioners, in their present treaty at Wickham.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E397_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201668</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862169</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862169</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160364</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86147)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160364)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 63:E397[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The heads of the great charge, presented to the Honourable House of Commons, against the eleven impeached members, by Colonel Scroope. Colonel Okey. Colonel Hewson. Colonel Pride. Lievt. Col. Bowen. Lievt. Col. Goffe Major Raynbow. Capt. Berry. Capt. Clarke. Capt. Carter. Capt Roase. Master Sexby Master Gettings. As also, certain papers from the army, setting forth the gallant proceedings of the commissioners, in their present treaty at Wickham.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Walton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>July 8. 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Expulsion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Impeachments --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:160364:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HEADS Of the great CHARGE <hi>PRESENTED</hi> To the Honourable Houſe of Commons, againſt the eleven impeached Members,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Colonel Scroope.</item>
                  <item>Colonel Okey.</item>
                  <item>Colonel Hewſon.</item>
                  <item>Colonel Pride.</item>
                  <item>Lievt. Col. Bowen.</item>
                  <item>Lievt. Col. Goffe</item>
                  <item>Major Raynbow.</item>
                  <item>Capt. Berry.</item>
                  <item>Capt. Glarke.</item>
                  <item>Capt. Carter.</item>
                  <item>Capt. Roaſe.</item>
                  <item>Maſter Sexby</item>
                  <item>Maſter Gettings.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AS ALSO,</hi> Certain <hi>Papers</hi> from the Army, ſetting forth the gallant proceedings of the <hi>Commiſſioners,</hi> in their preſent Treaty at <hi>Wickham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Walton,</hi> July 8. 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:160364:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:160364:2"/>
            <head>The proceedings of the late Treaty, betwixt the Parliaments Commiſſioners, and the Army.</head>
            <p>THere came Letters alſo to the Houſe, from the Commiſſioners with the Army, and tharein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed two letters from the Generall dated <hi>Iuly</hi> firſt at <hi>Wickam,</hi> whereof one of them gave to underſtand that the Generall had that day appointed Lievtenant Generall <hi>Crumwell,</hi> Commiſſary Gen. <hi>Ireton,</hi> Col. <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> Col. <hi>Rainsborow,</hi> Col. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> Colonel Sir <hi>Hardreſſe Waller,</hi> Col. <hi>Rich,</hi> Col. <hi>Lambert,</hi> Col. <hi>Hammond,</hi> and Major <hi>Rainsborow;</hi> theſe or any five of them, of which the Major part to be of the five laſt to treate and debate with the Commiſſioners of Parliament upon the papers, and deſires ſent from the army to the Parliament, and the Votes ſent to the army according to the Order of both Houſes of the 26 of Iune, 1647. And the other letter was in anſwer to the Vote of the Houſe on Tueſday laſt, that a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular charge ſhould be delivered into the Houſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the 11 Members by this day, the Generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning this anſwer thereunto, That as he finds a great willingneſſe in his councell of war, to anſwer the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the houſe in all things ſo in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar but the things being of that importance to the Kingdome and the perſons charged ſo many in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:160364:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> taken up more time then was expected, and therefore deſire that it may be reſpited until Tueſday next, at which time they will not faile to bring it in, and that the Kingdome ſhall then ſee they have not impeached the Gentlmen out of any private reſpects but in affection, and duty to the publique.</p>
            <p>There was further alſo a Proclamation from the Generall, forbiding any abuſe or obſtruction to be offered to any Officers of Parliament in levying the Exciſe or other aſſeſſements.</p>
            <p>From the army came further this evening, that His Majeſty one Thurſday from Hatfield toward winſor where he expected to ſee his children, of which he was very deſierous, but intended not to ſtay there above a day or tſio, but remove ſome further diſtance from London. The treaty with the Parliaments Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſioners, and Commiſſioners from the Army began this morning, as was appointed, the head quarters of the army it is ſuppoſed will be removed Saturday to <hi>Reading.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The houſe had ſome debate of the Prince Electors deſires, and ordered to leave it to his own pleaſure.</p>
            <p>A letter was read in the houſe from the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners with the army, giving to underſtand their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon treaty with the army, &amp; the manner of their proceedings. The houſe upon debate approve of the Commiſſioners proceedings therein.</p>
            <p>The head quarters of the army it is certified were removed this day to Reading and his Majeſty was gon back from Winſor to the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> houſe neer <hi>Cauſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="text">
               <body>
                  <pb facs="tcp:160364:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Fryday Iuly</hi> 2. His Excellency appointed, theſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Army to treate with the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from the Parliament in theſe words:</head>
                  <p>I Do hereby appoint Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary Generall <hi>Ireton,</hi> Colonell <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> Colonel <hi>Rainsborough,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Harriſon,</hi> Colonel Sir <hi>Hardres Waller,</hi> Colonel <hi>Rich,</hi> Colonel <hi>Lambert</hi> Colonel <hi>Hammond</hi> and Major <hi>Disborough;</hi> Theſe ten or any five of them (of which the major part to be of the five laſt) to Treate and Debate with the Right Honourable, The Commiſſioners of Parliament reſiding with the Army, upon the Papers and Deſires ſent from the Army to both Houſes, and the Votes ſent to the Army, according to the effect of the Order of both Houſes, dated the 26 of June, 1647. And for that purpoſe to attend the Comiſſioner; at their lodging at the Katherine wheel to-morrow morning by eight, of the clock and ſo from time to time, and place to place as ſhall be mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually agreed on.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given under my Hand and Seale at <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> 
                        <date>the firſt day of July, 1647.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>His Excellency having alſo received certain votes of the houſe touching the eleven members impeached, ſent this enſuing letter in anſwer thereto.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Right Honourable the Commiſſioners of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment now reſiding with the Army.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HAving with my Councel of Warre conſidered of the Votes of the Houſe of Commons, <hi>Iune</hi> 29. which you ſent me, for the bringing in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar charg and proofes againſt the Members charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Army, by Fryday next at fartheſt: As I find a great willingneſſe in them to anſwer the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Houſe in all things, ſo in particular, but
<pb facs="tcp:160364:4"/>the things being of that importance to the Kingdom, and the perſons charged ſo many in number, hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up more time then was expected; Wee deſire therfore, That it may be reſpited untill Tueſday next at which time we ſhall not faile to bring it in; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we could wiſh that no time might bee loſt therein which might be improved for the preſent ſettlement of the affaires of this Kingdome, and that the Kingdome ſhall then ſee, we have not impeached the Gentlemen out of any private reſpects, but in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and duty to the Publique. I remaine</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Wickham,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Iuly</hi> 1. 1647.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your very affectionate. Friend and Servant,</hi> Tho: Fairfax.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>At a councell of of war at the Generals quarters at <hi>Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> yeſterday being the 5 day of Iuly, 1647. It was ordered as followeth. <hi>Ordered by his Excellency and the Councell of war, that the Officers and Souldiers under mentioned, doe re-repaire to London, for preſenting of the Charge againſt the</hi> 11 <hi>members to the houſe of his Excellency and the whole Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the making of this order, was a very great Councell of war, conſiſting of eleven Col. ſeven Lievtenants Col. and Majors, with a great number of Captaines.</p>
            <p>The names of the officers aforeſaid mentioned, appointed to preſent the charge againſt the eleven members are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Col. Scroope, Col. Okey, Col. Hewſou, Col. Pride, Lieut. Col. Bowyer, Lieut. Col. Goffe. Maj. Raignbow, Cap. Berry, Cap. Clarke, Cap. Roafe, Mr. Sexby, and Mr. Getting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to the Order of the Councel of Warre before reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Commanders thereby nominated, for preſenting the Charge againſt the eleven Members, came to London to deliver the particular Charge to the Houſe. The Charge it ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, more then one ſheete; therefore of neceſſity muſt here be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb facs="tcp:160364:4"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Thurſday Iuly <hi>1.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>The Generall advanced this day to <hi>Wickham,</hi> and the Kings Majeſty came from <hi>Hatfield,</hi> dined at <hi>Moore-Park</hi> neere <hi>Watford,</hi> and thence rode to <hi>Windſor;</hi> but his Majeſty finding his deſires not anſwered, ſo as to have the opportunity of rejoycing in the ſociety of his Children there, he left the place the next day, and went to <hi>Winchomb</hi> houſe, neere <hi>Reading.</hi> In this his Majeſties progreſſe, the Country flockt together to ſee him; before him rode a Trumpeter, then ſome Perſons of Honour bare headed; after this came his Majeſty attended by the Commiſſioners, and about a mile behind them marched a Regiment of Horſe.</p>
                  <p>The laſt Lords day, Maſter Crofts preached before the King in the preſence chamber, at the Lord Cravens houſe neare Cauſum bridge, in the fornoone, and Maſter Peters below in the Hall, and in the afternoone the King heard di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſervice onely.</p>
                  <p>The Head-quarters continue at <hi>Reading;</hi> ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints have beene made to the Generall, of abuſes committed by divers Souldiers; and for prevention thereof for the future, his Excellency ſet forth a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, charging and requiring all Soldiers what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, to forbear taking of horſes from any perſon whatſoever, without ſufficient Warrant or to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell any Perſon where they quarter to give them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny money, and in further purſuance thereof, his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency granted Commiſſion to the Colonell, Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Colonell, or Major of every Regiment, for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of offences by a Councell of Warre in each Regiment, a copy whereof followeth: <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:160364:5"/>
            <head>The heads of the Charge preſerted to the Houſe of Commons, July 6.</head>
            <p>FIrſt, that they have endeavoured to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Rights and Liberties of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, and to ſtand in oppoſition againſt the true courſe of Juſtice, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That by falſe informations, and evill ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, they have uſed their utmoſt endeavours to raiſe a miſ-underſtanding betwixt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Army.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That they have been obstructive inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the ſervice of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves very forward for the obſtructing of that Deſigne.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> That they have endeavoured to ſet an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my on foot within this Kingdome, and have alſo endeavoured to carry on many deſperate deſignes within this Realm.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, that the Army doth intend to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt ſome of the impeached Members firſt, and ſo to the next by degrees. The Charge was read in the Honourable Houſe of Commons upon Tueſday laſt, and after ſome debate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the further reſult thereof was put off till Fryday following.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
